Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin 1778 April-December Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Dohrman, Arnold Henry. Lisbon
    Account of the foundering of an American ship, named Heart of Oak, off the costs of Portugal; aid he has given to the officers and sailors who were saved from the wreck; will procure them a passage to America or France; tells this to Franklin to prove his friendship for America and his willingness to render greater services if it is in his power.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Assistance rendered Captain Cumstock, who lately escaped from prison; both he and Mr. Chandler in want. Prize sent into Brest by the Ranger, Captain Jones. Desires an apartment near Franklin's taken for him at Passy.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Dowse, Nathaniel. Bordeaux
    Sailed from Virginia, April 14, 1777, as commander of the ship Mercer; his crew rose against him on the 4th of May and carried the vessel into Whitehaven, whence his escape and final arrival at Bordeaux. Begging to know if they have any employment for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Courter, Harmon. Boston
    Safe arrival at Boston after a rough passage of fifty-one days, also the arrival of Captain Nicholson at Portsmouth and Mr. Deane at Plymouth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    Sending the enclosed, which have just arrived from London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 6; Mem. 2p.; Lefebvre de Longeville,-----. Paris
    Proposal to sell a type-founding plant to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Barre, -----. Merseilles
    Desires to serve under the American generals; sends a memoir in which his military services and his request are both set forth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Lorthe, Gabriel-Antoine de. Bordeaux
    Had the honor of calling on Franklin in Philadelphia and following with Mr. Roger his experiments in electricity; takes for granted Franklin's knowledge of mathematics; asks his advice therefore on the works enclosed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Charost, Armand-Joseph de Béthune, duc de. Paris
    Recommending le Sieur Despret who has been employed in the management of the vessels now being built by his house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Received the good news of their alliance with France. Opinion in America of Lord North's policy; extreme measures advocated against Great Britain. Thanking him for his kindness to Jonathan. Arrival of Mr. Holker in fine health and spirits. Everybody pleased with the enclosed Resolve of Congress. News of his family and friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Arrenberg, Reinier. Rotterdam
    Desiring an answer upon the affair of the English bibles which Franklin designed to have printed in Holland; begs for authentic news from America as the news in the English Gazette is nearly all false. Congratulates him on the happy change in the affairs of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Malibran, Jh. Paris
    Enclosing a letter from an old friend of his in Barcelona; if Franklin desires an interview relative to this friend's affairs, will wait on him at any appointed time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Lefebvre de Longeville,-----. Paris
    Desires to send him a memoir, showing the advantages to accrue to America from the acquisition of a foundry.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Recommending Tessier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 8; 4p.; The Prevost d'Exmes. Paris
    Address to Dr. Franklin on his mission to France. A. poem.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 8; A.L.S. 5p.; Simpson, Thomas. Brest
    Account of his conduct which led Commodore Jones to suspend and put him under arrest. Requests a fair and open trial and if his trial cannot be brought on in Brest that they will order him to be sent immediately to America to take his trial there. Refers to a letter written to them by John Langdon, of Portsmouth, for his character.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Simpson, Thomas. Brest
    Narrating in detail his conduct from the time Captain Jones put him in charge of the English man-of war, Drake, to his arrival in Brest, a prisoner, placed under arrest by Captain Jones for a breach of his orders; denies having disobeyed him; begs for a fair trial, if possible, in America; can never serve his country under the command of Captain Jones.
    (Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 8; A.L.S. 1p.; ----- Niou, ainé. Brest
    Announcing the arrival of John Paul Jones, with an English man-of-war, taken after a bloody fight.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 9; L. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Ranger," Brest
    Announcing his arrival with the British ship of war, Drake, the English colors inverted under the Amercian stars; has brought in nearly two hundred prisoners; advises their exchange or their being sent back to America on the Drake; has suspended and confined Lieutenant Simpson for disobedience of orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 9; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bertin, Madame. Paris
    Begging Messrs. Franklin and Lee to dine with her on Saturday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?] May 9; A. L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafreté, M. and Mme de
    Inviting Franklin, his grandson, and Mr. Adams to dine with them at Suresnes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 9; D. S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; By The Continental Congress
    Forbidding the American Commissioners to recommend foreign officers for the navy of the United States.
    Printed in Journals of Congress, Phila. [1779], IV, 276.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 9; L .S. 1p.; S. and J.H. Delap. Bordeaux
    Enclosing two letters that have arrived for Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Deucher, Riedy and Co. Nantes
    Offering to procure a passage to Virginia for a Member of Congress who he hears desires to return to his country by the first opportunity; begs Franklin to speak to the Minister in order to hasten the sailing of the vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 9; A.L.S. 1p.; La Blancherie, Claude-Mammès de Pahin Champlain de
    A multitude of occupations has prevented his testifying his gratitude to Franklin; will make amends at his first leisure moment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 9; A.L.S. 2p.; La Porte, ----- de
    A young French officers desires to enter the service of the Colonies; has all the talents of a brave officer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Seguin, ------. Lacuepède
    With reference to Jean Jerome Seguin who wishes to obtain some employement in the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.] May 10; L. 2p.; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    Is there any truth in the report thet General Washington is grown unpopular, that his arny deserts in great number and that the sufferings of the Americans are excessive? The Commissioners feel assured that the terms they are empowered to offer by the Conciliatory Bills, though much short of independence, will be accepted. Messages to Franklin from various friends; Mr. Curtis and Mr. Webb both broken and ruined.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse (Gamache), comtesse de Forbach and duchesse douairière de
    Her affection for him and her regrets that she will not see him till the following winter. The interest she has in his glory and success and the keen desire she for news of all which concerns him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 10; L. 1p.; Aguiton, ------. Paris
    Sets out for London the next day and offers to execute any commands Franklin may honor him with.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 10; A.L.S. 2p.; La Grange, ------ de
    Unable to support his family, consisting of a wife and five children, on the slender pittance he receives; in want of the very necessaries of life; begs assistance; refers him to various people for the truth of these assertions.
    (In French, in duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Flottes de Raissan, Antoine. Paris
    His admiration for Franklin; begs for a moment's audience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Information of the arrival of Captain Jones with a prize of sixteen guns.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Sparre, [J.] de. Strasbourg
    The plan he addressed to M. de Sartine concerning the United Colonies. Desires Franklin to employ him either in America or in his own town. Proposals he has had to enter the service of England, all of which he has rejected.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Malibran, Jh. Paris
    Desiring to know if Franklin received the letter he sent him from M. Tilebein, of Barcelona.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Desportes, Dalmas. Franconville
    Believes he can be useful to the Colonies in his capacity as a lawyer.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Gallent action performed by Captain Jones; his intention to equip the Drake and send the prisoners in her to America; money needed to do this.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Arrival of the brig Peggy from North Carolina, laden with tobacco; Captain Tucker and himself making all expedition to get the Boston ready for sea. Jersey privateers seen hovering along the coast of Spain and, owing to that country's neutrality, even enter their ports. The Marquis D'Armando named as Spanish Ambassador for the Court of Great Britain; expected at Bordeaux the next day on his way to England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 12; A.L.S. 2p. A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Asking for the loan of fifteen more guineas and promising to repay the entire debt in a short time; he and Mrs. Melmoth ready to start for England in a day or two; begs him to keep the fact a secret.
    Franklin's answer enclosed. Inconvenience he experienced in favouring him with the fifty guineas; relies on his honor and punctuality for a speedy repayment; sorry to hear that his trip to England must be kent secret.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Concerning an offer made to Mr. Livingston of a vessel to be completely fitted out and armed, provided they will grant a commission; advance in rank this will give Mr. Livingston on his arrival in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 12; A.L.S. 2p.; de Milly, Comte. Paris
    Asking his protection for M. Douson, a surgeon of talent, who desires employment in the armies of the Americans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 12; A.L.S. 1p.; de Cossé,Marquis. Paris
    Recommending M. de Masson; his knowledge of politics and familiarity with various language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 12; Mem. 2p.; Bouffé, Gabriel et al
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to purchase land for them, near Philadelphia.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 12.; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Has induced certain Dutch merchants, friends of his, to send a vessel directly to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 12; Mem. S. 2p.; Bouffé, Gabriel et al
    Wish to purchase lands near Philadelphia and request Dr. Frankllin to have the purchase made by some trustworthy person on the spot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roux, C.J. Paris
    While Franklin works for the happiness of men, he occupies himself with that of children; hopes his writings on the subject may merit Franklin's approbation.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Account from Lisbon of the arrival of the Peace and Plenty, privateer fom Belfast, bringing in the brig Dolphin, Captain Turner, from Boston; Captain Turner destroyed the despatches from Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Arnold, George. Maycnce
    Wishes to know if the General Arnold of whom he reads so often in the newspapers is his son, from whom he has not heard for some years; his name, birth-place and station, as the son of a butcher, tally exactly with his son's history.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Montessuy, D. Paris
    His wish to obtain from the Colonies timber, hemp, resin and tar for the supply of the Royal Marine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 13; A.L.S. 1p.; La Corbière, ----- de
    M. le Comte de Maillebois desired to interest Franklin on behalf of their boarding-school for girls.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Hornbostel, J. C. Marseilles
    Requesting the position of Consul at Marseilles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Montcarel, Jean-Jacques Le Goüeslier de. Marseilles
    Enclosing letters from M. de la Radière to his son in America.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1778 May 14; L.S. Richard Henry Lee, James Lovell. 5p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. Yorktown, Pa
    Good condition of affairs in America. The low political methods of the English Court. The treaty with France.
    Printed in Wharton's Diplom. Corres. of the Amer. Rev., II, 574.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 14; A.L.S. 4p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Reminding Franklin of the merchant at Brest who desired to become the representative of Congress at that port. Sends the enclosed note in favor of le Chevalier de Bazantin; sure that a recommendation from Franklin would do much towards procuring liberty to those unfortunate officers. Messages from Mme. la Douairière des Deuxponts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 14; A.L.S. 2p.; La Blancherie, Claude-Mammès de Pahin Champlain de
    Charged by M. Le Roy to inform Franklin that the members of the Academy of Sciences have appointed him one of four commissioners; names the time of the meeting, which he hopes Franklin will honor with his presence. Sends him a translation of Volta on the inflammable air of swamps.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Lotbinière, Michel-Alain Chartier de. Paris
    Begging him to see that the enclosed letter from M. Holquart gets safely to its destination in America and begs him to say a few words in his favor to M. de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Gadsden, Christopher. Charlestown
    Introducing Mr. Thomas Waites who goes to France on business for the common cause.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 14; A.L.S. sam[uel] Ph[ili]ps Savage, Pres[iden]t. 2p.; The Board of War
    Captain Courter has been assisted on his journey to Congress. Captain Senneville has been received with every mark of attention. The improved outlook in America following the treaty with France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Hubbart, Tuthill. Boston
    Enclosing a letter from Aunt Mecom to Franklin; account circulated of Franklin's life having been attempted and of his being left in a languishing condition; the real pleasure the news of his welfare gave his friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Didelot, Jean-François. Paris
    Asking his good offices in favor of M. Gellée.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Carmier, Andrew. Calais
    Offering his services for the position of Consul at Calais; refers him to M. Grand for further particulars.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Deane., 1778 May 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Livingston, Abraham. Charlestown
    Requesting his advice and assistance for Mr. Jos. Brown who is on a tour of Europe.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 15; A.L.S. Richard Henry Lee and James Lovell. 3p.; The Continental Congress, Committee for Foreign Affairs. Yorktown
    Amount of tobacco lost in the attempt to send it to France; advantage of France opening the trade from her own ports. Reasons why Congress think it best to expunge Articles 11 and 12 from the treaty with France. Doubtful which to wonder at more, the folly of the English in making themselves so hated or their scandalous barbarity in the expression of their resentment. Concerning the contract which the Commercial Committee has signed with the agent of Mr. Beaumarchais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 15.; L. in 3d P. 1p.; O'Gorman, Thomas, chevalier
    Has returned from Burgundy and desires to pay his respects to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Hutton, James
    Acknowledging his favor of the 10th inst. Concerning passports to insure the safety of the sloop, Good Intent, which goes from London to Labrador with articles for the use of the Indians and missionaries. Does not even yet despair of peace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 15; A.L.S. 6p.; Hodge, William. Cadiz
    Enclosing copies of two letters sent to the Governor of Cadiz, one relative to the English Consul claiming three sailors belonging to Captain Conyngham; the other concerning three American prisoners who swam ashore from an English frigate, but were retaken and probably suffered death for desertion. The number of prisoners who make their escape and arrive at Cadiz in the most destitute condition.
  - to Edward Bancroft, 1778 May 15; A.L. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel
    General Burgoyne arrived in London to get the convention confirmed; but this will not be done. Mr. Hartley told Lord Camden that he was sure the Commissioners, and particularly Dr. Franklin, were much discontented with their situation at Paris, for they might as well, he said, live at the Bastile as be exposed, as they were, to the perpetual observaton of the French Ministerial spies. Lord Camden says he has good reasons to believe another ministerial negotiator went to have a talk with the Commissioners.
    (In cipher.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 16; A.L. 14p.; Paine, Thomas. Yorktown
    Gives a detailed history of military affairs since the 11th of September, including the actions at Brandywine and Germantown and some minor expeditions; his final arrival n Yorktown; his publication of the Crisis No. 5 to General Howe; has begun No. 6 which he intends addressing to Lord North. Lord Howe's contemptible affair of December 4th; his report to Lord Germain, representing Washington's camp as a strongly fortified place, is absolutely false. Description of the camp at Valley Forge; thinks the fighting is nearly over; England has done her utmost. Desires to consult Franklin about the History of the American Revolution. News of the Commissioners having sailed from England. Message to William Temple Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Paine, Thomas. Yorktown
    Has sent him a long letter [IX, 173], but in case it should not come to hand, mentions certain of its contents.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 16; Mem. S. Benj. Hill and twenty-four others. 3p.; The Sailors put on the Drake. Brest
    Testifying in favor of Lieutenant Simpson's conduct on board the Drake.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 16; A.L.S. William Ellery, Richard Hutson, Thomas Adam. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Commerce. York, Pa
    Concerning the contract between the house of Roderique, Hortalez and Co., and the Committee of Commerce; instructions on that head. The obstructions of the bays and harbors to the southward has prevented the intended shipping of tobacco. Congratulates them on the treaties.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Sutaine de Bourez, —. Paris
    Concerning the papers of his nephew Du Coudray.
  - to Franklin and Adams, 1778 May 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Authur. Chaillot
    Enclosing certain important papers; they will make such alterations as they judge proper; dreadful consequences to be expected from the disobedience and extravagance of certain subordinate servants.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Valtravers, Rodolph. Bienne
    Afraid Franklin's letters are subject to inspection; directions in case their correspondence should be more regularly established in favor of both the American and Swiss Cantons by the mediation of France. Manner in which a mutual, sincere friendship between the two republics might be brought about; suggests several particular considerations of true interest on both sides; offers his services to promote such an alliance; for this he would need credentials and some pecuniary assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Penet, P. Paris
    Concerning the sale of the two vessels, Le Lion and le Duc de Choiseul.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 May 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Christian Stenger and William Stragham. Brest
    A petition from the captains of the Dolphin and Lord Chatham, captured by Captain Jones, begging Franklin to procure their deliverance; their families entirely dependent on their industry; the best means to adopt, in order to secure their liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 18; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Ruault, -----. Paris
    Sending the large dictionary of the Academy and nine volumes of Abbé de Mably's works.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Dupuy, Ferrand. Paris
    Requesting his intervention and assistance for a young man who had volunteered his services to the United States and was taken prisoner when his vessel was captured by the English on the voyage to Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 18; L.S. 4p.; Defrancq, J.J. Orchimont
    Begs Franklin to procure him some civil or military employment.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Deane, 1778 May 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Captain Jones has received a letter from Mr. Schweighauser who, in consequence of one from Mr. Lee, claims the disposal of the prizes sent into this port by the "Ranger." He informs Captain Jones that he has the management of public business and that Mr. Williams pretends to what he alone has authority for. Mr. Williams came bither with the sole view of assisting Captain Jones in his affairs and has not attempted to alter the channel the commercial part of the business has taken. The sale of the "Lord Chatham" will probably be made by the Admiralty, if not, it will fall into the hands of Mr. Bersoll, by whom the "Ranger" was furnished and to whom Captain Jones has applied for his present wants. The "Drake" is fitting to convey the prisoners to America. Captain Jones's great object to secure the release of two hundred American prisoners in exchange for those he captured; possibility of effecting this exchange in France; in that case suggests their purchasing the "Drake" to carry their supplies to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 18; A.L.S. 5p.; Le Fort, Marc. Marseilles
    Enclosing an extract from a letter from Antoine Gautier, with information of the capture of the vessel, L'Elégante, Captain Collineau; begs Franklin to write to the General Counsel or the Congress, at Williamsburg, for a detailed account of what happened and whether any part of the cargo or its value can be recovered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, John
    Reasons why it would be more prudent for him to obtain an approved certificate of his nationality as an American. Departure of the Boston. Report from Martinique of an American frigate being blown up in an engagement with a sixty-four-gun ship; only four lives saved. News of the French, English and Spanish squadrons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 19; A.L.S. 2p.; de Bongars, Chevalier. Traillet par Eu
    Asking for a commission in the army for a French gentleman of noble birth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; du Buat, -----. St. Malo